<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="lib/rfc2629.xslt"?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc linkmailto="no" ?>
<?rfc editing="no" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc-ext allow-markup-in-artwork="yes" ?>
<?rfc-ext include-index="no" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY MAY "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>MAY</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY MUST "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>MUST</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY MUST-NOT "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>MUST NOT</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY OPTIONAL "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>OPTIONAL</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY RECOMMENDED "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY REQUIRED "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>REQUIRED</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY SHALL "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>SHALL</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY SHALL-NOT "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>SHALL NOT</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY SHOULD "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>SHOULD</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY SHOULD-NOT "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
  <!ENTITY rfc793 SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0793.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc6824 SYSTEM
  "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6824.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc1122 SYSTEM
  "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1122.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc3360 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3360.xml">
]>

<rfc
    category="info"
    ipr="noModification3978"
    docName="draft-bonaventure-mptcp-reset" >
    <!-- Processing Instructions- PIs (for a complete list and description,
          see file http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html and below... -->

    <!-- Some of the more generally applicable PIs that most I-Ds might want to use -->
    
    <!-- Try to enforce the ID-nits conventions and DTD validity -->
    <?rfc strict="yes" ?>

    <!-- Items used when reviewing the document -->
    <?rfc comments="no" ?>  <!-- Controls display of <cref> elements -->
    <?rfc inline="no" ?>    <!-- When no, put comments at end in comments section,
                                 otherwise, put inline -->
    <?rfc editing="no" ?>   <!-- When yes, insert editing marks: editing marks consist of a 
                                 string such as <29> printed in the blank line at the 
                                 beginning of each paragraph of text. -->

    <!-- Create Table of Contents (ToC) and set some options for it.  
         Note the ToC may be omitted for very short documents,but idnits insists on a ToC 
         if the document has more than 15 pages. --> 
   <?rfc toc="yes"?>
   <?rfc tocompact="yes"?> <!-- If "yes" eliminates blank lines before main section entries. -->
   <?rfc tocdepth="3"?>    <!-- Sets the number of levels of sections/subsections... in ToC --> 

    <!-- Choose the options for the references. 
         Some like symbolic tags in the references (and citations) and others prefer 
         numbers. The RFC Editor always uses symbolic tags.
         The tags used are the anchor attributes of the references. --> 
    <?rfc symrefs="no"?>
    <?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?> <!-- If "yes", causes the references to be sorted in order of tags.
                                 This doesn't have any effect unless symrefs is "yes" also. -->

    <!-- These two save paper: Just setting compact to "yes" makes savings by not starting each 
         main section on a new page but does not omit the blank lines between list items. 
         If subcompact is also "yes" the blank lines between list items are also omitted. -->
    <?rfc compact="yes" ?>
    <?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
    <!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->

    <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

<front>
    <title abbrev="MPTCP Reset">Processing of Reset segments by
    Multipath TCP</title>

    <author initials="O." surname="Bonaventure" fullname="Olivier Bonaventure">
      <organization>UCLouvain</organization>
      <address>
        <email>Olivier.Bonaventure@uclouvain.be</email>
        <uri>http://inl.info.ucl.ac.be/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2014"/>
    <area>Transport</area>
    <workgroup>MPTCP</workgroup>
    <keyword>MPTCP</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document discusses how a Multipath TCP implementation
	should generate and process RST segments. </t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Editorial Note (To be removed by RFC Editor)">
      <t>
        Discussion of this draft takes place on the MPTCP working group mailing list
        (multipathtcp@ietf.org), which is archived at <eref
        target="http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/multipathtcp/"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        Working Group information can be found at <eref
        target="http://tools.ietf.org/wg/mptcp/"/>; 
      </t>
    </note>

</front>
<middle>

<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
<t>
   The Transmission Control Protocol (TCP) <xref target="rfc793"/> was
   designed to provide a reliable data transfer between hosts attached
   to a single IP address. Multipath TCP <xref target="rfc6824"/> is a
   recent extension that enables a single TCP connection to use
   multiple paths. For Multipath TCP, each path corresponds to a TCP
   connection established between the communicating hosts. Each of
   these connections is identified by the classical four-tuple (source
   and destination IP addresses and source and destination port
   numbers). Multipath TCP allows to group several of these TCP
   connections, called subflows in <xref target="rfc6824"/> inside a
   single Multipath TCP connection. It should be noted that the number of
   subflows that are used for a given Multipath TCP connection is not
   fixed and can change during the lifetime of a Multipath TCP
   connection. 
</t>
<t>
   In regular TCP, the RST flag is used to abruptly terminate a TCP
   connection. When a host receives a valid TCP segment with the RST
   flag, it immediately terminates the connection. This causes the
   loss of all in-flight data that has not yet been acknowledged. In
   the original TCP specification, a host could generate a segment
   with the RST flag in the following cases: 
</t>
<t>
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>
       A host receives a non-SYN segment that corresponds to a TCP
       connection that does not exist (anymore). 
    </t>
    <t>
       A host receives a SYN segment and does not want to establish
       the requested connection for any reason. 
    </t>
    <t>
      A host does not have enough resources anymore (e.g. memory) to 
      support the established connection. 
    </t>
    <t>
      The corresponding connection has been idle for a long time and
      no answer has been received to the keepalive segments that the
      host has sent over this TCP connection. 
    </t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
   Over the years, other reasons to use the RST flag have been added
   to TCP implementations. The most important one is the possibility
   for an application, typically a server, to abruptly terminate a TCP
   connection by forcing the stack to send a segment with the RST flag
   instead of waiting for the normal FIN exchange and being forced to
   maintain state during $obo$.
</t>
<t>
   Despite the fact that TCP is a transport protocol that is used only
   on endhosts, various types of middleboxes are known to spoof TCP
   segments that contain the RST flag to abruptly terminate TCP
   connections $NDSS$. Some of these middleboxes terminate TCP connections to
   block some applications such as P2P file transfers, others provide
   security services such as DPI and terminate TCP connections once
   they have identified suspicious data in the payload. This behavior
   of middleboxes has been considered as harmful in <xref target="rfc3360"/>.
</t>
<t>
   Multipath TCP cannot simply behave like regular TCP when
   transmitting and receiving TCP segments with the RST flag. Since a
   Multipath TCP connection is composed of several TCP subflows, the
   transmission or reception of a TCP connection on a subflow only
   terminates the corresponding subflow. This does not necessarily
   terminate the Multipath TCP connection. 
</t>
<t>
  This document is organized as follows. We discuss in section $ob$
  the reasons why a Multipath TCP host could decide to transmit a RST
  segment. In section $ob$, we propose a new Multipath TCP option that
  can be used inside RST segments to convey additional information
  about the reason for this RST segment and explain how a Multipath
  TCP host should react to such segments.
</t>

<section title="Notational Conventions" anchor="notational-conventions">
<t>
  The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD",
  "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
  interpreted as described in <xref target="rfc2119"/>.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section title="Generation of RST segments" anchor="generation">
<t>
   This section documents the various reasons why a Multipath TCP host
   could generate a segment with the RST flag. 
</t>
<section title="Lack of ressources" anchor="rst_ressources">
<t>
   A Multipath TCP implementation cannot usually support an unlimited
   number of TCP subflows associated to a single Multipath TCP
   connection. A Multipath TCP implementation may face a lack of
   ressources when :
</t>
<t>
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>
       It receives a SYN segment and accepting this subflow would 
       exhaust the subflow table of the host. This error condition it
       typically permanent.
    </t>
    <t>
       It experiences memory pressure and needs to recover additional
       ressources. Under these circumstances, it could decide to
       terminate some subflows for some Multipath TCP
       connections. This error condition is typically transient. 
    </t>
  </list>
</t>
</section>

<section title="Administratively prohibited" anchor="rst_admin">
<t>
   A Multipath TCP implementation can be configured with policies that
   determine which subflows can be associated to a given Multipath TCP
   connection. These policies could be specified on a per application
   basis, a per host basis or via other means that are outside the
   scope of this document. Based on this configuration, a Multipath
   TCP could generate a RST segment to refuse the establishment of a
   subflow when : 
</t>
<t>
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>
       It receives a SYN segment from a source address that conflicts
       with its policies. For example, an enterprise server could be
       configured to only accept subflows that originate from the
       enterprise subnet and not from the global Internet. 
       This error condition it typically permanent.
    </t>
    <t>
       It receives a SYN segment destined to a destination address that conflicts 
       with its policies. For example, a server may be configured to only expose 
       some of its addresses to a subset of its clients. This error 
       condition is typically permanent. 
    </t>
    <t>
       It receives a SYN segment destined to a destination port that conflicts 
       with its policies. For example, a web server may be configured
       to only accept subflows targeted to port 80 even if the
       Multipath TCP specification allows to group together subflows
       on different destination ports. This error 
       condition is typically permanent. 
    </t>
  </list>
</t>
</section>

<section title="Too many already acknowledged data" anchor="rst_toomanydata">
<t>
   Multipath TCP allows data that was transmitted over one subflow to
   be retransmitted over another subflow. This situation can happen
   during a handover when a mobile host moves from one access network
   to another. In this case, the same data can be transmitted twice
   over different subflows. This is mandated by Multipath TCP to
   ensure that any middlebox on the path of the first subflow will see
   in-sequence segments. However, retransmitting already acknowledged
   data over a subflow is not the best utilisation of the network
   ressources as reported in $INFOCOM2014$. It should be possible for
   a Multipath TCP host that has too many data that has already been
   acknowledged over one subflow but still needs to be retransmitted
   over another subflow to preserve the subflow ordering to terminate
   the subflow with too many outstanding but already acknowledged
   data. Measurements or simulations are required to evaluate the best
   threshold to be used by a Multipath TCP implementation to decide
   when to terminate such a subflow. In this document, we propose to
   terminate a subflow once there are more than one initial congestion
   window's worth of data that are outstanding on this subflow but
   have already been acknowledged over another subflow. 
</t>
<t>
  The situation described above is obviously transient. The
  termination of such a subflow does not indicate that the path should
  not be used anymore. Instead, the reception of a RST segment
  indicating such a cause should trigger the reestablishment of a
  subflow over this path. The host that sends such a RST segment could
  also send a SYN segment at the same time. However, it should be
  noted that there are situations such as a server sending the RST
  segment to a client connected behind a NAT where only the host that
  receives the RST segment is able to reestablish the subflow. When
  the new subflow is established, data transfer starts at the data
  sequence number that was reached on the other subflows and the
  outstanding and unacknowledged data do not need to be retransmitted.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Unacceptable performance" anchor="rst_badperformance">
<t>
  A Multipath TCP host can send data over several subflows. Some of
  these subflows may perform well while the performance of others
  could be affected by various performance problems :
</t>
<t>
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>
      Excessive delay compared to the other subflows. If the receive
      window used by Multipath TCP is too small, sending data over a
      long delay subflow would reduce the overall performance of the
      Multipath TCP connection. 
    </t>
    <t>
       Excessive losses. The Multipath TCP congestion control scheme
       tries to move traffic away from congested paths. If one of the
       subflows is more heavily congested than the others, this can
       severely impact the performance of the Multipath TCP
       connection. 
    </t>
    <t>
       Excessive reordering. Excessive reordering at the subflow level
       may lower performance by making TCP's retransmission techniques
       less reactive. 
    </t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
  A Multipath TCP host that detects that the performance of a
  Multipath TCP connection is severely affected by one of the
  underlying subflows, it could decide to terminate the offending
  subflow. Depending on the number of remaining active subflows, it
  may be needed to reestablish another subflow to replace the
  terminated one.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Lifetime expired" anchor="rst_lifetime">
<t>
  A Multipath TCP connection is composed of several subflows. However,
  maintaining a large number of subflows can be costly from an
  implementation viewpoint. A Multipath TCP host should monitor the
  usage of the underlying subflows and could terminate one subflow
  when  :
</t>
<t>
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>
      The subflow has been active for more than a given configured
      time. Some implementations might want to bound the lifetime of
      subflows like web servers bound the lifetime of HTTP/1.1
      sessions. 
    </t>
    <t>
       No reply has been received to keepalive probes. The keepalive
       probes <xref target="rfc1122"/> can be used over each subflow
       to verify that their paths and the remote host are still
       active. If no answer is received to these probes, the
       corresponding subflow should be terminated. The Multipath TCP
       connection could be terminated once the last subflow is
       terminated. 
    </t>
  </list>
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section title="The MPTCP Reset option" anchor="mptcp_reset">
  <t>
   The Multipath TCP specification <xref target="rfc6824"/> defines
   several Multipath TCP options. Each option is encoded by using the
   Type-Length-Value format shown in the figure below.
 </t>
<figure>
  <artwork type="option">
                        1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +---------------+---------------+-------+-----------------------+
   |     Kind      |    Length     |Subtype|                       |
   +---------------+---------------+-------+                       |
   |                     Subtype-specific data                     |
   |                       (variable length)                       |
   +---------------------------------------------------------------+

</artwork>
<postamble>
   The Multipath TCP option format.
</postamble>
</figure>
<t>
   The proposed format for the Multipath TCP RST option is defined in
   the figure below. 
</t>
<figure>
  <artwork type="option">
                      1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +---------------+---------------+-------+-----------------------+
 |     Kind      |    Length     |Subtype|R a m| res.| Reason    |  
 +---------------+---------------+-------+-----------------------+
 |           Data ACK (4 or 8 octets, depending on flags)        |
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
 |   Data sequence number (4 or 8 octets, depending on flags)    |
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
 |              Subflow Sequence Number (4 octets)               |
 +-------------------------------+-------------------------------+
 |                  Sender's truncated HMAC (64 bits)            |
 |                                                               |
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
</artwork>
<postamble>
   The proposed Multipath TCP RST option format.
</postamble>
</figure>

<t>
   The Multipath TCP RST option contains a reason code that allows the
   sender of the option to provide more information about the reason
   for the termination of the subflow. <xref target="rfc793" /> allowed
   the utilisation of the segment payload to provide additional
   information about the reason for the termination of a TCP
   connection and some middleboxes have used this facility
   $NDSS$. However, without a precise format for the reason code, the
   only thing that TCP implementations could do with this payload was
   to log the received data. With a specific reason field, it becomes
   possible for a Multipath TCP implementation to intelligently and
   correctly react to the termination of a subflow. 
</t>
<t>
  The Multipath TCP RST option also contains authentication
  information. Given the importance of middleboxes in today's Internet
  and knowing that some of them send spoofed RST segments, it is
  important for a Multipath TCP host to distinguish between a RST
  segment that was generated by the remote host and a RST segment that
  was generated by a middlebox on the path.
</t>
<t>
  To prevent replay attacks, authentication information should be
  computed over fresh data that is sent by the remote host. In the
  case of a RST segment, this is obviously not possible. To
  authenticate the RSP segment and prevent the replay from one RST segment
  to another subflow, the HMAC field contained the low order 64 bits
  of the HMAC computed by using the sender's key over the entire MPTCP
  RST option. The information contained in the MPTCP RST option is
  essentially the same as the one present in the DSS option. In fact,
  the MPTCP RST option can be considered as being equivalent to a zero
  byte mapping. The subflow sequence number, Data ACK and Data
  Sequence number must have the same value as if a mapping was sent
  over this subflow. 
</t>
<t>
  Like the DSS option, the MPTCP RST option has a variable length
  depending on the utilization of 32 bits or 64 bits Data sequence
  numbers and Data acknowledgements. The `a` and `m` flags have the
  same role as in the DSS option.
</t>
<t>
  The `R` flag is used by the sender to indicate whether it requests
  the recipient of the RST segment to reestablish a subflow over the
  same path upon reception of this RST segment. If set to 1, the
  remote host should try to reestablish a subflow on the same path as
  the terminated one. 
</t>
<t>
  The `Reason` code is a 6 bits field that indicates the reason for
  the termination of the subflow. The following codes are defined in
  this document :
</t>
<t>
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>
      Lack of ressources (code TBD). This code indicates that the
      sending host does not have enough ressources to support the
      terminated subflow. 
    </t>
    <t>
       Administratively prohibited (code TBD). This code indicates
       that the requested subflow is prohibited by the policies of
       the sending host.
    </t>
    <t>
       Too many already acknowledged data (code TBD). This code indicates 
       that there are too many data that need to be transmitted over 
       the terminated subflow while having already been acknowledged 
       over one or more other subflows. 
    </t>
    <t>
       Unacceptable performance (code TBD). This code indicates 
       that the performance of this subflow was too low compared to 
       the other subflows of this Multipath TCP connection. 
    </t>
    <t>
       Lifetime expired (code TBD). This code indicates 
       that the lifetime of the subflow has expired. 
    </t>


  </list>
</t>

</section>

<section title="Processing the MPTCP RST option" anchor="rst_processing" >
<t>
   TODO
</t>
</section>


<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana-considerations" >
<t>
   <cref>To be provided.</cref>
</t>
</section>

<section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security-considerations">
<t>
   <cref>To be provided.</cref>
</t>
</section>

<section title="Conclusion" anchor="conclusion">
<t>
   To be written
</t>
</section>

<section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="acknowledgements" >
<t>
  To be provided.
</t>

</section>

</middle>
  
<back>

<references title="Normative References">

<reference anchor="RFC2119">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
    <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner">
      <organization>Harvard University</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="1997" month="March"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
  <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
</reference>



</references>

<references title="Informative References">

<reference anchor="RFC2119">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
    <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner">
      <organization>Harvard University</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="1997" month="March"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
  <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
</reference>


</references>



  </back>

</rfc>
