<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="lib/rfc2629.xslt"?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc linkmailto="no" ?>
<?rfc editing="no" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc-ext allow-markup-in-artwork="yes" ?>
<?rfc-ext include-index="no" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY MAY "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>MAY</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY MUST "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>MUST</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY MUST-NOT "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>MUST NOT</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY OPTIONAL "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>OPTIONAL</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY RECOMMENDED "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY REQUIRED "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>REQUIRED</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY SHALL "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>SHALL</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY SHALL-NOT "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>SHALL NOT</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY SHOULD "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>SHOULD</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY SHOULD-NOT "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
  <!ENTITY RFC0793 SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0793.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC6824 SYSTEM
  "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6824.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC1122 SYSTEM
  "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1122.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC3360 SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3360.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC5961 SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5961.xml">
 <!ENTITY RFC6528 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6528.xml">
]>

<rfc
    category="info"
    ipr="trust200902"
    docName="draft-bonaventure-mptcp-reset" >
    <!-- Processing Instructions- PIs (for a complete list and description,
          see file http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html and below... -->

    <!-- Some of the more generally applicable PIs that most I-Ds might want to use -->
    
    <!-- Try to enforce the ID-nits conventions and DTD validity -->
    <?rfc strict="yes" ?>

    <!-- Items used when reviewing the document -->
    <?rfc comments="no" ?>  <!-- Controls display of <cref> elements -->
    <?rfc inline="no" ?>    <!-- When no, put comments at end in comments section,
                                 otherwise, put inline -->
    <?rfc editing="no" ?>   <!-- When yes, insert editing marks: editing marks consist of a 
                                 string such as <29> printed in the blank line at the 
                                 beginning of each paragraph of text. -->

    <!-- Create Table of Contents (ToC) and set some options for it.  
         Note the ToC may be omitted for very short documents,but idnits insists on a ToC 
         if the document has more than 15 pages. --> 
   <?rfc toc="yes"?>
   <?rfc tocompact="yes"?> <!-- If "yes" eliminates blank lines before main section entries. -->
   <?rfc tocdepth="3"?>    <!-- Sets the number of levels of sections/subsections... in ToC --> 

    <!-- Choose the options for the references. 
         Some like symbolic tags in the references (and citations) and others prefer 
         numbers. The RFC Editor always uses symbolic tags.
         The tags used are the anchor attributes of the references. --> 
    <?rfc symrefs="no"?>
    <?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?> <!-- If "yes", causes the references to be sorted in order of tags.
                                 This doesn't have any effect unless symrefs is "yes" also. -->

    <!-- These two save paper: Just setting compact to "yes" makes savings by not starting each 
         main section on a new page but does not omit the blank lines between list items. 
         If subcompact is also "yes" the blank lines between list items are also omitted. -->
    <?rfc compact="yes" ?>
    <?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
    <!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->

    <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

<front>
    <title abbrev="MPTCP Reset">Processing of Reset segments by
    Multipath TCP</title>

    <author initials="O." surname="Bonaventure" fullname="Olivier Bonaventure">
      <organization>UCLouvain</organization>
      <address>
        <email>Olivier.Bonaventure@uclouvain.be</email>
        <uri>http://inl.info.ucl.ac.be/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="C." surname="Paasch" fullname="Christoph Paasch">
      <organization>UCLouvain</organization>
      <address>
        <email>Christoph.Paasch@uclouvain.be</email>
        <uri>http://inl.info.ucl.ac.be/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="G." surname="Detal" fullname="Gregory Detal">
      <organization>UCLouvain</organization>
      <address>
        <email>Gregory.Detal@uclouvain.be</email>
        <uri>http://inl.info.ucl.ac.be/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2014"/>
    <area>Transport</area>
    <workgroup>MPTCP</workgroup>
    <keyword>MPTCP</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document discusses how a Multipath TCP implementation
	should generate and process RST segments. </t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Editorial Note (To be removed by RFC Editor)">
      <t>
        Discussion of this draft takes place on the MPTCP working group mailing list
        (multipathtcp@ietf.org), which is archived at <eref
        target="http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/multipathtcp/"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        Working Group information can be found at <eref
        target="http://tools.ietf.org/wg/mptcp/"/>; 
      </t>
    </note>

</front>
<middle>

<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
<t>
   The Transmission Control Protocol (TCP) <xref target="RFC0793"/> was
   designed to provide a reliable data transfer between hosts attached
   to a single IP address. Multipath TCP <xref target="RFC6824"/> is a
   recent extension that enables a single TCP connection to use
   multiple paths. For Multipath TCP, each path corresponds to a TCP
   connection established between the communicating hosts. Each of
   these connections is identified by the classical four-tuple (source
   and destination IP addresses and source and destination port
   numbers). Multipath TCP allows to group several of these TCP
   connections, called subflows in <xref target="RFC6824"/> inside a
   single Multipath TCP connection. It should be noted that the number of
   subflows that are used for a given Multipath TCP connection is not
   fixed and can change during the lifetime of a Multipath TCP
   connection. 
</t>
<t>
   In regular TCP, the RST flag is used to abruptly terminate a TCP
   connection. When a host receives a valid TCP segment with the RST
   flag, it immediately terminates the connection. This causes the
   loss of all in-flight data that has not yet been acknowledged. In
   the original TCP specification, a host could generate a segment
   with the RST flag in the following cases: 
</t>
<t>
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>
       A host receives a non-SYN segment that corresponds to a TCP
       connection that does not exist (anymore). 
    </t>
    <t>
       A host receives a SYN segment and does not want to establish
       the requested connection for any reason. 
    </t>
    <t>
       A host has tried to retransmit the same data too many times
       without having received an acknowledgment. 
    </t>
    <t>
      The corresponding connection has been idle for a long time and
      no answer has been received to the keepalive segments that the
      host has sent over this TCP connection  <xref target="RFC1122"/>
    </t>
    <t>
      A host does not have enough resources anymore (e.g. memory) to 
      support the established connection. 
    </t>

  </list>
</t>
<t>
   Over the years, other reasons to use the RST flag have been added
   to TCP implementations. The most important one is the possibility
   for an application, typically a server, to abruptly terminate a TCP
   connection by forcing the stack to send a segment with the RST flag
   instead of waiting for the normal FIN exchange and being forced to
   maintain state.
</t>
<t>
   Despite the fact that TCP is a transport protocol that is used only
   on endhosts, various types of middleboxes are known to spoof TCP
   segments that contain the RST flag to abruptly terminate TCP
   connections . Some of these middleboxes terminate TCP connections to
   block some applications such as P2P file transfers, others provide
   security services such as DPI and terminate TCP connections once
   they have identified suspicious data in the payload. This behavior
   of middleboxes has been considered as harmful in <xref target="RFC3360"/>.
</t>
<t>
   Multipath TCP cannot simply behave like regular TCP when
   transmitting and receiving TCP segments with the RST flag. Since a
   Multipath TCP connection is composed of several TCP subflows, the
   transmission or reception of a TCP connection on a subflow only
   terminates the corresponding subflow. This does not necessarily
   terminate the Multipath TCP connection. 
</t>
<t>
  This document is organized as follows. We discuss in section <xref
  target="generation" />  the reasons why a Multipath TCP host could decide to transmit a RST
  segment. In section <xref target="mptcp_reset" />, we propose a new Multipath TCP option that
  can be used inside RST segments to convey additional information
  about the reason for this RST segment and explain how a Multipath
  TCP host should react to such segments.
</t>

<section title="Notational Conventions" anchor="notational-conventions">
<t>
  The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD",
  "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
  interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section title="Generation of RST segments" anchor="generation">
<t>
   This section documents the various reasons why a Multipath TCP host
   could generate a segment with the RST flag. 
</t>
<section title="Lack of ressources" anchor="rst_ressources">
<t>
   A Multipath TCP implementation cannot usually support an unlimited
   number of TCP subflows associated to a single Multipath TCP
   connection. A Multipath TCP implementation may face a lack of
   ressources when :
</t>
<t>
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>
       It receives a SYN segment and accepting this subflow would 
       exhaust the subflow table of the host. This error condition it
       typically permanent.
    </t>
    <t>
       It experiences memory pressure and needs to recover additional
       ressources. Under these circumstances, it could decide to
       terminate some subflows for some Multipath TCP
       connections. This error condition is typically transient. 
    </t>
  </list>
</t>
</section>

<section title="Administratively prohibited" anchor="rst_admin">
<t>
   A Multipath TCP implementation can be configured with policies that
   determine which subflows can be associated to a given Multipath TCP
   connection. These policies could be specified on a per application
   basis, a per host basis or via other means that are outside the
   scope of this document. Based on this configuration, a Multipath
   TCP could generate a RST segment to refuse the establishment of a
   subflow when : 
</t>
<t>
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>
       It receives a SYN segment from a source address that conflicts
       with its policies. For example, an enterprise server could be
       configured to only accept subflows that originate from the
       enterprise subnet and not from the global Internet. 
       This error condition is typically permanent.
    </t>
    <t>
       It receives a SYN segment destined to a destination address that conflicts 
       with its policies. For example, a server may be configured to only expose 
       some of its addresses to a subset of its clients. This error 
       condition is typically permanent. 
    </t>
    <t>
       It receives a SYN segment destined to a destination port that conflicts 
       with its policies. For example, a web server may be configured
       to only accept subflows targeted to port 80 even if the
       Multipath TCP specification allows to group together subflows
       on different destination ports. This error 
       condition is typically permanent. 
    </t>
  </list>
</t>

<t>Both ICMPv4 and ICMPv6 contain error code that can be used to
indicate similar error conditions. However, ICMP messages are more
likely to be dropped by network equipment than TCP segments. 
Multipath TCP's reaction to these ICMP messages and the TCP RST segments should be similar. 

</t>

</section>

<section title="Too many already acknowledged data" anchor="rst_toomanydata">
<t>
   Multipath TCP allows data that was transmitted over one subflow to
   be retransmitted over another subflow. This situation can happen
   during a handover when a mobile host moves from one access network
   to another. In this case, the same data can be transmitted twice
   over different subflows. This is mandated by Multipath TCP to
   ensure that any middlebox on the path of the first subflow will see
   in-sequence segments. However, retransmitting already acknowledged
   data over a subflow is not the best utilisation of the network
   ressources as reported in <xref target="INFOCOM2014" />. It should be possible for
   a Multipath TCP host that has too many data that has already been
   acknowledged over one subflow but still needs to be retransmitted
   over another subflow to preserve the subflow ordering to terminate
   the subflow with too many outstanding but already acknowledged
   data. Measurements or simulations are required to evaluate the best
   threshold to be used by a Multipath TCP implementation to decide
   when to terminate such a subflow. In this document, we propose to
   terminate a subflow once there are more than one initial congestion
   window's worth of data that are outstanding on this subflow but
   have already been acknowledged over another subflow or there is no
   other data on this subflow. 
</t>
<t>
  The situation described above is obviously transient. The
  termination of such a subflow does not indicate that the path should
  not be used anymore. Instead, the reception of a RST segment
  indicating such a cause should trigger the reestablishment of a
  subflow over this path. The host that sends such a RST segment could
  also send a SYN segment at the same time. However, it should be
  noted that there are situations such as a server sending the RST
  segment to a client connected behind a NAT where only the host that
  receives the RST segment is able to reestablish the subflow. 
</t>
</section>

<section title="Unacceptable performance" anchor="rst_badperformance">
<t>
  A Multipath TCP host can send data over several subflows. Some of
  these subflows may perform well while the performance of others
  could be affected by various performance problems :
</t>
<t>
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>
      Excessive delay compared to the other subflows. If the receive
      window used by Multipath TCP is too small, sending data over a
      long delay subflow would reduce the overall performance of the
      Multipath TCP connection. This error condition is typically transient. 
    </t>
    <t>
       Excessive losses. The Multipath TCP congestion control scheme
       tries to move traffic away from congested paths. If one of the
       subflows is more heavily congested than the others, this can
       severely impact the performance of the Multipath TCP
       connection. This error condition is typically transient. 
    </t>
    <t>
       Excessive reordering. Excessive reordering at the subflow level
       may lower performance by making TCP's retransmission techniques
       less reactive. This error condition is typically transient. 
    </t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
  A Multipath TCP host that detects that the performance of a
  Multipath TCP connection is severely affected by one of the
  underlying subflows, it could decide to terminate the offending
  subflow. Depending on the number of remaining active subflows, it
  may be needed to reestablish another subflow to replace the
  terminated one.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Lifetime expired" anchor="rst_lifetime">
<t>
  A Multipath TCP connection is composed of several subflows. However,
  maintaining a large number of subflows can be costly from an
  implementation viewpoint. A Multipath TCP host should monitor the
  usage of the underlying subflows and could terminate one subflow
  when  :
</t>
<t>
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>
       No reply has been received to keepalive probes. The keepalive
       probes <xref target="RFC1122"/> can be used over each subflow
       to verify that their paths and the remote host are still
       active. If no answer is received to these probes, the
       corresponding subflow should be terminated. The Multipath TCP
       connection could be terminated once the last subflow is
       terminated. Note that sending a regular RST over each subflow
       will only terminate the subflow but not the Multipath TCP connection.
    </t>
  </list>
</t>
</section>

<section title="Removed address" anchor="rst_rmaddr">

<t>When a host receives a REMOVE_ADDR option, it should send a TCP
keepalive over each of the subflows using the removed address. If a
response to the keepalive is received, the subflow should not be
terminated. Otherwise, the lack of response to the keepalives will
trigger a termination of the subflow as explained in section <xref target="rst_lifetime"/>.
</t>
<t>
When a host sends a REMOVE_ADDR option, it SHOULD send a RST segment
over each of the subflows that were using the removed address.
</t>

</section>


<section title="Middlebox interference has been detected" anchor="rst_middlebox">

<t>
  As explained in <xref target="RFC6824"/>, Multipath TCP includes
  several mechanisms to detect and possibly cope with middlebox
  interference. There are unfortunately cases where Multipath TCP
  needs to terminate a subflow once it has detected middlebox
  interference. The following cases are listed in <xref target="RFC6824"/> : 
</t>
<t>
 <list style="symbols">
   <t>
     As explained on page 42 of <xref target="RFC6824"/>, a host MUST
     close a subflow with a RST if the first ACK that it receives over
     this subflow does not contain the DSS option.
   </t>
   <t>
     As explained on page 43 of <xref target="RFC6824"/> a host MUST
     close a subflow by sending a RST segment with the MP_FAIL option
     if it receives a segment with an invalid DSS checksum. The
     MP_FAIL option includes the data sequence number of the first
     byte of the payload of the affected segment.
   </t>
 </list>
</t>

</section>

<section title="Multipath TCP specific errors" anchor="rst_mptcp">

<t>
  <xref target="RFC6824"/> lists several error conditions that are
  specific to Multipath TCP and may lead to the termination of a
  subflow by transmitting a RST segment. These error conditions are : 
</t>
<t>
 <list style="symbols">
   <t>A SYN segment with the MP_JOIN option was received with an 
   invalid HMAC or an unknown token. In this case, the host may reply with a RST or 
   silently ignore the error (<xref target="RFC6824" /> pages 22, 23
   and 45). 
   </t>
   <t>A TCP segment is received without a DSS checksum on a Multipath
   TCP connection where the usage of the checksum has been negotiated 
   (<xref target="RFC6824" /> page 24). 
   </t>
   <t>
   No DSS mapping has been received within a window of data (<xref
   target="RFC6824"/> page 27).     
   </t>
  </list>
</t>
</section>

<section title="Fast Close" anchor="rst_fastclose">
<t>
The MP_FASTCLOSE option is defined in <xref target="RFC6824"/> allows
to quickly terminate a Multipath TCP connection. This operation is
described in section 3.5 of <xref target="RFC6824"/>.
</t>

</section>

<section title="Unspecified TCP error" anchor="rst_error">
<t>
A TCP implementation may send a RST segment for reasons that are
unrelated to Multipath TCP. 

</t>

</section>

</section>



<section title="The MPTCP Reset option" anchor="mptcp_reset">
  <t>
   The Multipath TCP specification <xref target="RFC6824"/> defines
   several Multipath TCP options. Each option is encoded by using the
   Type-Length-Value format shown in the figure below.
 </t>
<figure>
  <artwork type="option">
                        1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +---------------+---------------+-------+-----------------------+
   |     Kind      |    Length     |Subtype|                       |
   +---------------+---------------+-------+                       |
   |                     Subtype-specific data                     |
   |                       (variable length)                       |
   +---------------------------------------------------------------+

</artwork>
<postamble>
   The Multipath TCP option format.
</postamble>
</figure>
<t>
   The proposed format for the Multipath TCP RST option is defined in
   the figure below. 
</t>
<figure>
  <artwork type="option">
                      1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +---------------+---------------+-------+-----------------------+
 |     Kind      |    Length     |Subtype|a m 0 T|    Reason     |  
 +---------------+---------------+-------+-----------------------+
 |           Data ACK (4 or 8 octets, depending on flags)        |
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
 |   Data sequence number (4 or 8 octets, depending on flags)    |
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
 |              Subflow Sequence Number (4 octets)               |
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+

</artwork>
<postamble>
   The proposed Multipath TCP RST option format.
</postamble>
</figure>

<t>
   The Multipath TCP RST option contains a reason code that allows the
   sender of the option to provide more information about the reason
   for the termination of the subflow. <xref target="RFC0793" /> allowed
   the utilisation of the segment payload to provide additional
   information about the reason for the termination of a TCP
   connection and some middleboxes have used this facility
   <xref target="NDSS" />. However, without a precise format for the reason code, the
   only thing that TCP implementations could do with this payload was
   to log the received data. With a specific reason field, it becomes
   possible for a Multipath TCP implementation to intelligently and
   correctly react to the termination of a subflow. 
</t>
<t>
  The Multipath TCP RST option also contains sequence number and
  acknolwedgement information to enable the receiving host to verify
  the validity of the RST segment. 
</t>
<t>
  Like the DSS option, the MPTCP RST option has a variable length
  depending on the utilization of 32 bits or 64 bits Data sequence
  numbers and Data acknowledgements. The `a` and `m` flags have the
  same role as in the DSS option.
</t>
<t>
  The `T` flag is used by the sender to indicate whether the error
  condition that is reported is Transient (T bit set to 1) or
  Permanent (T bit set to 0). If the error condition is considered to
  be Transient by the sender of the RST segment, the recipient of this
  segment MAY try to reestablish a subflow over the failed path. If
  the error condition is considered to be permanent, the receiver of
  the RST segment SHOULD not try to reestablish a subflow over this
  path. 
</t>
<t>
  The `Reason` code is an 8 bits field that indicates the reason for
  the termination of the subflow. The following codes are defined in
  this document :
</t>
<t>
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>
      Lack of ressources (code TBD1). This code indicates that the
      sending host does not have enough ressources to support the
      terminated subflow. This error condition is usually transient.
    </t>
    <t>
       Administratively prohibited (code TBD2). This code indicates
       that the requested subflow is prohibited by the policies of
       the sending host. This error condition is usually permanent.
    </t>
    <t>
       Too many already acknowledged data (code TBD3). This code indicates 
       that there are too many data that need to be transmitted over 
       the terminated subflow while having already been acknowledged 
       over one or more other subflows. This error condition is 
       usually transient.
    </t>
    <t>
       Unacceptable performance (code TBD4). This code indicates 
       that the performance of this subflow was too low compared to 
       the other subflows of this Multipath TCP connection. This error condition is 
       usually transient.
    </t>
    <t>
       Lifetime expired (code TBD5). This code indicates 
       that the lifetime of the subflow has expired. This error condition is 
       usually transient.
    </t>
    <t>Removed address (code TBD6). This code indicates that the
    address associated to this subflow has been removed by the
    sender. This error condition is usually permanent.
    </t>
    <t>Middlebox interference (code TBD7). Middlebox interference has
    been detected over this subflow. This error condition is permanent.
    </t>
    <t>
      Multipath TCP specific error (code TBD8). An error has been
      detected in the processing of Multipath TCP options. This error
      is usually permanent.
    </t>
    <t>Fast Close (code TBD9). This RST segment has been sent in
    response to a segment with the MP_FASTCLOSE option. This error
    condition is permanent since the Multipath TCP connection is being closed.
    </t>
    <t>Unspecified TCP error (code TBD10). An unspecified TCP error has
    been detected on the affected subflow. This error condition can be
    transient or permanent.
    </t>

  </list>
</t>

</section>

<section title="Processing the MPTCP RST option" anchor="rst_processing" >
<t>
   The MPTCP RST option defined in this document can only appear in
   segments having the RST bit set. If a host receives the MPTCP RST
   option in a non-RST option, it MUST silently discard the received
   segment and ignore its content.
</t>
<t>
   When receiving a RST segment containing the MPTCP RST option, a
   host MUST first verify the validity of the segment by checking that :
</t>
<t>
  <list>
    <t> the 
  </list>

</t>


</section>


<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana-considerations" >
<t>
   This document request the allocation of a new MPTCP option sub-type
   from IANA. Furthermore, it defines a set of error conditions that
   can be encoded inside the MPTCP RST option. This list of error
   conditions should be maintained by IANA.
</t>

<texttable anchor="table_iana" title="Suggested MPTCP RST codepoints">
    <ttcol align='center'>Codepoint #</ttcol>
    <ttcol align='center'>Reason</ttcol>
    <c> TBD1</c>
    <l>Lack of ressources</l>
    <c> TBD2</c>
    <l>Administratively prohibited</l>
    <c> TBD3</c>
    <l>Too many unacknowledged data</l>
    <c> TBD4</c>
    <l>Unacceptable performance</l>
    <c> TBD5</c>
    <l>Lifetime expired</l>
    <c> TBD6</c>
    <l>Removed address</l>
    <c> TBD7</c>
    <l>Middlebox interference detected</l>
    <c> TBD8</c>
    <l>Multipath TCP specific error</l>
    <c> TBD9</c>
    <l>Response to Fast Close</l>
    <c>TBD10</c>
    <l>Unspecified TCP error</l>
    <postamble>Suggested codepoints for the MPTCP RST option</postamble>
</texttable>

<t>

</t>

</section>

<section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security-considerations">
<t>
   <cref>To be provided.</cref>
Discuss <xref target="RFC5961"/> ? and <xref target="RFC6528"/>
</t>
</section>

<section title="Conclusion" anchor="conclusion">
<t>
   To be written
</t>
</section>

<section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="acknowledgements" >
<t>
  This work was partially supported by the FP7 Trilogy2 project.
</t>

</section>

</middle>
  
<back>

<references title="Normative References">

<reference anchor="RFC2119">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
    <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner">
      <organization>Harvard University</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="1997" month="March"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
  <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
</reference>

 &RFC0793;
 &RFC6824;
 &RFC3360;
 &RFC1122;
 &RFC5961;
 &RFC6528;

</references>

<references title="Informative References">

<reference anchor="NDSS">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="">Detecting Forged TCP Reset Packets</title>
    <author initials="N." surname="Weaver" fullname="Nick Weaver">    </author>
    <author initials="R." surname="Sommer" fullname="Robin Sommer">    </author>
    <author initials="V." surname="Paxson" fullname="Vern Paxson">    </author>
    <date year="2009" month="March"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="NDSS" value="2009"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="INFOCOM2014">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="">Cross-Layer Path Management in Multi-path Transport Protocol for Mobile Devices</title>
    <author initials="Y.-S." surname="Lim" fullname="Yeon Sup Lim">    </author>
    <author initials="Y." surname="Chen" fullname="Yung Chen">    </author>
    <author initials="E." surname="Nahum" fullname="Erich Nahum">
    </author>
    <author initials="D." surname="Towsley" fullname="Don Towsley">    </author>
    <author initials="K." surname="Lee" fullname="Kang-Won Lee">    </author>
    <date year="2014" month="April"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="IEEE INFOCOM" value="2014"/>
</reference>

</references>



  </back>

</rfc>
